<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A double catechisme one more large, following the order of the common authorized catechisme, and an exposition thereof: now this second time published: the other shorter for the weaker sort: both set forth for the benefit of Christian friends and wel-willers. By Richard Bernard, Master of Arts, and preacher of Gods word at Worsop in Nottingham-shire.</title>
            <title>Large catechisme</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849017</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849017</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09077)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 699:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A double catechisme one more large, following the order of the common authorized catechisme, and an exposition thereof: now this second time published: the other shorter for the weaker sort: both set forth for the benefit of Christian friends and wel-willers. By Richard Bernard, Master of Arts, and preacher of Gods word at Worsop in Nottingham-shire.</title>
                  <title>Large catechisme</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A revised version of: Bernard, Richard.  A large catechisme (first published in STC 1955.5, with the short catechism.</note>
                  <note>Both large and small catechisms are reprinted in STC 1953.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacking leaves C4-5.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14145:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Double Catechiſme, one more large, following the order of the common authorized Catechiſme, and an expoſition thereof: now this ſecond time publiſhed: the other ſhorter for the weaker ſort: both ſet forth for the benefit of Chriſtian friends and wel-willers.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Bernard,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Preacher of Gods word at <hi>Worſop</hi> in <hi>Nottingham-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. TIM. 4. 1. 2.</bibl>
               <p>I charge thee before God, and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall iudge the quicke and dead, at his appearing, and in his kingdome, preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>r. Pet. 2. 2.</bibl>
               <p>As new-borne babes deſire that ſincere milke of the word, that ye may grow thereby.</p>
            </q>
            <p>CAMBRIDGE, Printed by <hi>Iohn Legate.</hi> 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14145:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14145:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull the towardly young Gentleman, and of great good hopes, <hi>M. William Caven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh,</hi> ſonne and heire to the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>William,</hi> Lord <hi>Cavendiſh,</hi> increaſe of all true honour and happines is moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſhed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Worſhipfull, it is written of one, a kings ſonne, that he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked 3. things at Gods hands, outward proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, inward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and ſuch glorie as ſhold be neither falſe nor fained. What more to be happy? The firſt of theſe you haue by birth, and your parents wealth &amp; honor: the ſecond, <hi>Salomon</hi> tels you, how you may haue, by the getting &amp; keeping a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> which is a continual feaſt: and the third is purchaſed for you by Chriſt, if you by faith can take hold of him, by whom (which is the true and greateſt glorie) we are made the ſonnes of
<pb facs="tcp:14145:3"/> God, and coheires with him of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God, and the vnſpeakable ioyes thereof. All theſe three muſt concurre to make a man bleſſed: no happineſſe in the firſt without the ſecond: no ſoundneſſe in the ſecond to abide without the third. Looſe Chriſt, a dew conſcience comforts: and outward goods and honour without inward health of grace, is an eſtate car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of eſtimation, but indeed hopeleſſe of the Saints bleſſed condition. Great wealth, &amp; noble birth, without the ſoules ſpirituall breath, is as a ſhippe vnder full ſaile in a tempeſtuous Sea without ſterne or Pylote: a caſe moſt daungerous: more like it is there ſhould be ſhipwracke, than that it ſhould come in ſafety to the hauen. Your ſhip is not yet at the ſea, you are but launching out, hitherto you haue lyen in harbour: ballance your ſoule with ſound knowledge, and holy affections before you aduenture: take with you your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, and be ſure you ſeaſon your fleſh with the ſalt of Gods word, leſt it corrupt at ſea, and you want neceſſaries, and be forced to go a ſhore before you come vnto your determined place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> telleth vs, that the young man which cheareth his heart vp in the dayes
<pb facs="tcp:14145:3"/> of his youth, to walke in the euill waies thereof, and in the ſight of his eyes, muſt know, that for theſe things <hi>God will bring him to iudgement:</hi> and therefore he adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him to remember his Creator in the dayes of his ſtrength, before the time come, when he ſhall confeſſe, that ſinne hath as much left him, as he it. Surely, Sir, if you betimes, as I hope you do, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord, and ſeeke him, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid to the child <hi>Salomon,</hi> he will be found of you: which he of his mercy graunt: but if you forſake him, he will forſake you; which God of his goodneſſe forbid. The aduancement of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> amongſt <hi>Pharaoes</hi> Princes, and <hi>Daniels</hi> honour aboue the great Baſſaes of Babylon, may ſhew you the truth of the one: and that young mans miſerable end, beautifull <hi>Abſolon,</hi> and <hi>Dauids</hi> deare ſonne, may ratifie the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of the other. Gods fauour is the fountaine of bliſſe, and in thoſe onely he delighteth that feare him.</p>
            <p>The good tokens of your good affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towards me, and towards the preachers of Gods word, the loue you do ſhew to further the paſſage of the Goſpell, both in word and liberall deeds, hath mooued me to offer this my labour vnto you: both
<pb facs="tcp:14145:4"/> to teſtifie my thankfulneſſe, and to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt vnto the world our good hopes of you, which I deſire that you may daily occaſion by holy fruites of obedience to be iuſtified of many, to Gods glory and your owne welfare.</p>
            <p>The Lord Almightie protect you and that honorable houſe whereof you are, and enlarge the name thereof, as with earthly renowne, ſo euer much more with ſpirituall bleſſings, that it wiſhing well to the Iſrael of God, peace and mercie may be vpon it: and the louing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God now ſhine vpon all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that hartily deſire the welfare of Sion, and the peace of Ieruſalem for euer.</p>
            <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Worſop,</hi> 
                  <date>the 28. of <hi>Nouember.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips euery way readie in all things in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Richard Bernard.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14145:4"/>
            <head>The Catechiſme.</head>
            <div type="question">
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> 
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OVV many things are needfull for you to vnderſtand, that you may knovv both God and your ſelfe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> Theſe 6. things: I. right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conceiue of God what he is, by his word and workes: II. to vnderſtand the creation: III. mans miſerie by the fall: IV. our redemption: V. our ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: VI. the certaintie of our glorification.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of God.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVho made yovv?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> God. Eſa. 42. 2. Gen. 26. 27.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat a one is God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> God is a ſpirit. Joh. 4. 24. Holy. Exod. 15. 11. Iuſt. Exod. 34. 6. and Mercifull. Exod. 34. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv many Gods are there?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> But onely one God, Deut. 6. 4. yet three perſons, Mat. 3. 16. 1. Ioh. 5. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich are the three perſons?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The Father begetting, the Sonne begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and the Holy Ghoſt proceeding, 2. Cor. 13. 13 Mat. 28. 19. and theſe three are God. Ioh. 1. 1. 1. Ioh. 5. 7. Act. 5. 3. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich of theſe three became man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſecond Perſon, Ieſus Chriſt, both God and man. Eſa. 9. 6. Heb. 2. 17.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14145:5"/>
               <head>Of our Creation.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Of vvhat did God make man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> His bodie was of duſt, the womans of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams ribbe, Gen. 2. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat a one did God make him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Both good. Gen. 2. 31. holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Gen 1. 26. Eph. 4. 28. Col. 3. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat vvas then mans eſtate and happines?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It was the ſtate of innocencie, without ſin or miſerie, and to God was he acceptable, Gen. 1 27. 31. &amp; 2. 25. &amp; 1. 28.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of mans fall and miſerie.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are you novv ſuch a one by birth, as he vvas by creation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Alas no: I am by nature full of ſinne, Pſ. 51. 5. Iob. 25. 4. 5. 6. Rom. 3. from verſ. 9. to 19. and ſo moſt miſerable. Iob 14. 1. 2. Rom. 5. 14. Eph. 2. 1. 2. 3. Rom. 3. 23. &amp; 2. 8. 9. and to God deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Pſal. 11. 5. Gal. 3. 10. Mat. 7. 23. &amp; 25. 41.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is ſinne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The breaking of Gods commandements, by thought word, or deed. 1. Ioh. 3. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv many commaundements are there?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Tenne. Deut. 10. 4. diuided into two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Deut. 4. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich be the commandements?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am the Lord thy God, &amp;c. Exod. 20. Deut. 5. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Do theſe ten commaund or forbid but onely vvhat is there ſet dovvne in ſhevv?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: they commaund or forbid, all the kinds contained vnder the ſame thing mentioned
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14145:5"/> and all the cauſes, with occaſions thereunto. 1. Ioh. 3. 15. Mat. 5. 28. 32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are they a prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No, nor ſo to be vſed: they are a rule for me to liue after, and do teach me my duty to God, and my neighbour. Deut. 6. &amp; 31. 12. Pſal. 119. 105. Eccleſ. 12. 13. Mat. 22. 37. 39.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is your duty tovvards God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> My dutie towards God, is to beleeue in him, to feare him, and to loue him, &amp;c. 2. Chron. 20. 20. Eccleſ. 12. 13. Mat. 22. 37.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is your duty tovvards your neighbour?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is to loue my neighbour as my ſelfe, &amp;c. Mat. 22 39. Rom. 13. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Can ye keepe the commaundements, and not offend God nor your neighbour?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: <hi>I</hi> breake them euery day, in thought, word, and deed, hating both God and my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by nature. Pſ. 14. 1. 2. 3. Rom. 8. 7. &amp; 1. 30. 2. Cor. 3. 5. Tit. 3. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is then novv your ſtate, and vvhat deſerue you by thus offending God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am in the ſtate of corruption and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue Gods curſe, which is eternall deſtruction of bodie and ſoule. Deut. 27. 26. Mat. 25. 41. 46. Gal. 3. 10.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of mans redemption.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are you in this caſe to do?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To cry vnto God for mercie, and ſeeke for deliuerance. Luk. 15. 17. Pſal. 51. 1. 2. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are you of your ſelfe able, or is there any good in you to moue God, to ſet you free?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No indeed, Rom. 3. 10. &amp; 7. 18. Luk. 17. 10. 2. Cor. 4. 4. Eph. 2. 8. 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14145:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Then vvho doth redeeme you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Onely Ieſus Chriſt, Rom. 7. 25 2. Cor. 5. 21 Rom. 5. 19. Gal. 2. 20. &amp; 3. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> He is the eternall Sonne of God, Mat. 17. 5. Heb. 1. 23. a King to gouerne vs, Pſ. 2. 6. Mat. 28. 18. a prieſt to offer for vs, Pſ. 110. 4. And a Prophet to teach vs, Deut. 18. 18. Eſa. 61. 1. Mat. 17. 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat beleeue you concerning him in the Articles of the Creed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 
                     <hi>I</hi> do beleeue, that he was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is this to you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I do perſwade my ſelfe hereby, that his puritie is for my corruption, his obedience for my tranſgreſſion, his death for my debt, and his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion for my eternall ſaluation. 1. Cor. 1. 30. Phil. 3. 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>But as God made all, vvill ſo Ieſus Chriſt alſo ſaue all?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No verily, many ſhall be damned, few ſhal be ſaued, Mat. 7. 13. 14. onely the elect, which take hold of Chriſt by a lively faith. Ioh. 3. 16. 36. Mar. 16. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is this liuely faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a true perſwaſion of my heart, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon Gods promiſes, Eph. 3. 17. Rom, 4. 21. that Ieſus Chriſt is giuen to me, Ioh. 3. 16. and the merits of his death and paſſion, are as truly mine, as if <hi>I</hi> my ſelfe had wrought them. 2. Cor. 5. 21. Rom. 8. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv come you by this faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> From my effectuall calling by the word preached, and the worke of Gods ſpirit. Act. 13. 48. Rom. 10. 14. 15. Eph. 1. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14145:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhere is ſet dovvne the ſumme of your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cefe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> In my Creed, <hi>I</hi> beleeue in God the Father Almightie. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are theſe a prayer, or ſo to be vſed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: it teacheth me what to beleeue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God and his church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat good hath Gods Church, the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers aboue the reſt of mankind?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> They are in the ſtate of grace, they haue communion with Chriſt, and one with another, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, the glorious reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the bodie, and life euerlaſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of ſanctification.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv may it appeare, that you haue this faith, and alſo theſe benefites?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By my ſanctification.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVho doth ſanctifie you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The holy Ghoſt, Rom. 15. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is ſanctification?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Jt is a making new of the whole man, whereby he daily dyeth to ſinne, and increaſeth in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, Eph. 4. 23. 24. Gal. 5. 24. 1. Theſ. 4. 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat grace proceedes from this ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> True repentance, leauing that which is ill with hatred, and performing new obedience with gladneſſe of heart continually, Ier. 31. 19. Act. 26. 20. Pſ. 119. 10. 113. 115. 136. 14. 34. 35. 44.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat eſtate novv ſtand you in, being ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and penitent?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 
                     <hi>I</hi> am in the bleſſed eſtate of grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if I continue, <hi>I</hi> ſhall inherite eternall life, Tit. 3.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14145:7"/> 4. 5. 6. 7. Rom. 11. 22. Mat. 10 22. 2. Tim. 4. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhy hath God thus made, redeemed, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and hitherto preſerued you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To ſerue him truly all the dayes of my life, Eph. 2. 10. Tit. 2. 11. 12. Luk. 1. 74. 75.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv must God be ſerued?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Onely after his will reuealed in hss writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word, Deut. 30. 8. 10. and 4. 2. 2. Cor. 4. 6.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of our ſtrengthening in the ſtate of grace, for the certainty of our glorification.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Js it needfull for ſuch as are elected, and once called, iuſtified, and ſanctified, that they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill in vſing meanes to ſaluation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yea truly: elſe they will fall away, Pro. 29. 18. 2. Chron. 15. 2. Heb. 3. 12. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat things muſt you continue in to aſſure your ſelfe of ſaluation, and to grovv ſtrong in the vvay of life?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Jn the knowledge of Gods word, Pſal. 11. 2. Act. 2. 42. 2. Pet. 1. 19. Ioh. 10. 27. 28. in faith, Joh. 3. 36. in loue to the godly, Ioh. 13 35. 1. Ioh. 3. 14. in obedience, Ezech. 36. 26. Pſal. 15. 5. Ier. 32. 39. 40. in patient ſuffering for Chriſt. Rom. 8. 17. Iam. 1. 12. in a longing after Chriſts comming, 2. Tim. 4. 8. in ſinceritie without hypocriſie, which will appeare by my appealing to God in theſe things, Ioh. 21. 15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Sacraments.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hath God giuen any helpes, and commaunded farther any other meanes beſides the vvord, for the ſtrengthening of vs herein?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14145:7"/>
                  <p>A. Yes, theſe two: Sacraments, and Prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is a Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> An outward ſigne and ſeale of inviſible gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv do the Sacraments ſtrengthen you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By a reuerent vſing and meditating of them rightly vnderſtood, as ſignes repreſenting Chriſt, and his benefites, and ſure ſeales of his couenant with vs, Gen. 9. 9. to 18. and 17. 9. 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hovv many Sacraments are there?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Onely two: Baptiſme, and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, 1. Cor. 10. 1. 2. 3. 4. Mat. 28. 19. &amp; 26. 29. 27. 1. Cor. 11. 23. 24. 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the ſigne, and the thing ſignified in Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſigne is water, and the grace is the bloud of Chriſt, by which I am waſhed from my ſinnes, Act. 2. 38. &amp; 22. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat are the ſignes and things ſignified in the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſignes are the bread and wine: the things ſignified, are the bodie &amp; bloud of Chriſt, 1. Cor. 11. 23. 24. 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hy come you to receiue?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To ſtrengthen my faith, and to keepe in remembrance Chriſt his death, till his comming againe, Rom. 4. 11. 1. Cor. 11. 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat ought you to do before you come?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Prepare my ſelfe by examination, 1. Cor. 11. 28.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat ought you to come vvith, to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> With foure things: 1. knowledge both of my miſerie, Gods mercie, and the doctrine of the Sacrament. 2. with faith in Ieſus Chriſt, Heb. 11. 6. 3. with repentance for all my ſinnes, Eſa. 1. 10. 11.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14145:8"/> 14. 15. 16. 4. with heartie loue vnto my neighbor, Mat. 5. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat if you come vnprepared vvithout theſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I come vnworthily, I am guiltie of the body and bloud of Chriſt, 1. Cor. 11. 27. I do eare and drinke my owne damnation, verſ. 29. God may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me, verſ. 40. and the diuell may enter into me, as he did vnto <hi>Iudas,</hi> and bring me to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of bodie and ſoule, Ioh 13. 27.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Prayer.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a right, heartie, and faithfull requeſt made vnto God, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, 1. Ioh. 5. 14. Rom. 8. 26. Iam. 1. 6. Ioh. 14. 14. &amp; 15. 16. Mat. 3. 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Can or doth euery one pray, that vttereth vvords, and vſeth a forme of prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a ſpeciall gift to Gods children, and ſuch onely pray, as haue knowledge what to aske, a hearty deſire in asking, and faith to beleeue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat direction of prayer haue you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſame which our Sauiour Chriſt taught his diſciples, <hi>Our Father vvhich art in heauen, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved be thy name. Thy kingdome come. Thy vvill be done in earth, as it is in heauen. Giue vs this day our daily bread: and forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as vve for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs. And lead vs not into temptation: but deliuer vs from euill.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat deſireſt thou of God in this prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I deſire my Lord God our heauenly Father who is the giuer of all goodneſſe, to ſend his grace vnto me, and to all people, that we may worſhip him, ſerue him, and obey him; as we ought to do. And I pray vnto God that he will ſend vs al things
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14145:8"/> that be needfull, both for our ſoules and bodies, and that he will be mercifull vnto vs, and forgiue vs our ſinnes, and that it will pleaſe him to ſaue and defend vs in all dangers ghoſtly and bodily, and that he will keepe vs from all ſinne and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and from our ghoſtly enemie, and from euerlaſting death. And this I truſt he will do of his mercie and goodneſſe, through our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: and therefore I ſay, Amen. So be it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14145:9"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme.</head>
               <head>Of new birth.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>WHat is your name?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 
                     <hi>Channauel,</hi> God is gracious to vs. <hi>Benalleuel.</hi> Loue wholy the Lord with the heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ho gaue you this name?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> My Godfathers and my Godmothers, who with my father, brought me to the Miniſter, into the congregation, to be baptized, and were eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall witneſſes of the ſame, and profeſſours of my faith and obedience to God for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhy vvere you baptized?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That <hi>I</hi> might receiue a badge of my Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, and be admitted into the Church, to liue amongſt the profeſſors of Chriſts name, &amp; to be receiued of them, and accounted as a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, the child of God, and an inheritour of the kingdome of heauen, vntill <hi>I</hi> ſhew the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhereby may you novv be certaine, that you are ſuch a one indeed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> If I do what my Godfathers and Godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did make profeſſion of for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> VVhat did your Godfathers and Godmothers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14145:9"/> make profeſſion of for you?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A</label> They did profeſſe three things in my name: the firſt was the forſaking of the diuell, and al his workes, the pompes, and the vanities of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world, and all the ſinfull luſts of the fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat vvere you then bound to them, that you haue promiſed to forſake them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yea verily, I am a bondſlaue to Sathan, by the corruption of my nature, prone to all vice, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſeed of all ſinne in me, and do hate both God and my neighbour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv can you then forſake this vvofull ſtate, and ceaſe from any euill, being thus bound and prone thereunto?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not by any naturall power in or of my ſelfe, but onely by the grace of God, when it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are you ſure you haue forſaken them, are you not deceiued?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am not deceiued: for I hate vnfainedly, the workes of the diuell, the worlds vanitie, all the vngodly manners of euery man: and I labour by all good meanes, to die to all ſinne daily, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the word of God, following it and all godly examples, indeauoring to kill ſpeedily euery ill motion, but cheriſhing the good in my heart, by meditation, vowes, faſting, and prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>But can you tell me, vvhat are the vvorkes of the diuell, the vvorlds vanitie, and the ill motions of the heart?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Whatſoeuer <hi>I,</hi> or any other, do thinke, ſpeake or do, againſt the will of God reuealed in his word written.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat hath mooued you to forſake the diuel, the vvorld, and the fleſh?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> For that I haue learned, and do well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14145:10"/> by knowledge from the word and mine owne experience, that theſe three, be the onely malicious, ſpirituall, powerfull, ſubtill, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall enemies of my eternall felicitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are the other things, that your God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers promiſed for you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Secondly, was the beleeeuing of all the twelue articles of my chriſtian faith, and the third was the learning diligently of Gods holy will and commaundements, and an obedient walking in the ſame, all the dayes of my life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q</label> 
                     <hi>VVhere is this vvill of God to be learned?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not from mine owne fantaſie, mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, traditions or examples of men, but onely out of the Scripture, which is the word written, by his Prophets and Apoſtles, in the bookes of the old and new Teſtament, which is ſufficient, to teach vs all things neceſſarie, that we need to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, for our ſaluation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat reaſons haue you to perſvvade your ſelfe, that this Scripture vvhich vve hold, is the true vvord of God, and none other?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Firſt, from the pen-men, being many and moſt of them ſimple and plaine perſons, who doe mutually conſent, ſetting downe their own faults without partialitie. Secondly, from the matter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue naturall mens reach; of mans creation, reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, laſt iudgement, and of the Trinitie in vnitie, prophecies alſo fulfilled in all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Thirdly, from the manner of ſpeaking, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily reproouing, or allowing, without ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reſpects. Fourthly, from the effect, binding conſcience, conuerting men, to hate euen life it ſelfe, for Gods glorie. Fifthly, the miraculous preſeruation thereof, with puniſhment of ſuch, as ſeeke to ouerthrowe either it, or the profeſſours
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14145:10"/> thereof. Laſtly, that it aſcribes all glorie to God, the maine end which it aymeth at.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat meanes muſt you vſe to come to the ſauing knovvledge of this vvord?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. Daily reading. 2. Learning the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, the grounds of religion. 3. Hearing the word with mind and affection, both read and preached publikely, by Gods miniſters. 4. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in mind, to vnderſtand the doctrine gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and in heart to affect the vſe made, after <hi>I</hi> haue either read or heard it. 5. Conference by as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſuperiours and Miniſters, by reaſoning with equals, and teaching inferiours, all in reuerence and humilitie, to vnderſtand that I know not, to be reſolued in that I doubt of, and to call to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, what <hi>I</hi> haue forgotten. 6. Continuall prayer with practiſe of it in my particular calling.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Do you thinke you are thus bound to forſake the diuell, the vvorld, and the fleſh, to beleeue in God, to learne to knovv and do his vvill, as they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed for you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes verily, and by Gods helpe ſo will I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to do, or elſe were I vnthankfull to God my Father, that hath called me into the ſtate of ſaluation, making me his child: and alſo vnmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of my ſureties, that haue ſo bound themſelues for me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>But tell me if any vndergo ſuch a charge, hovv can any be ſuretie to God for you, that you ſhould doe as they haue promiſed for you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Being aſſured by faith, that the ſeed of the faithfull are bleſſed, they iudging me charitably to bee one of them, did promiſe by the grace of God belonging vnto me in Chriſt, and the meanes which they would vſe, <hi>J</hi> ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14145:11"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are the meanes vvhich they haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to vſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I ſhould be taught ſo ſoone as I ſhall be able to learne, what a ſolemne vow, promiſe and profeſſion, I. haue made by them. II. That they will exhort me to heare ſermons, and to learn all things, which a Chriſtian ought to know for his ſoules health: but eſpecially the principles of religion, conteined in theſe foure: the Creed, the Lords prayer, the ten Commaundements, and the doctrine of the Sacraments.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Let vs then ſee, vvhether they haue vſed thoſe meanes, and hovv you haue profited, rehearſe the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of your beleefe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I beleeue in God the Father almightie, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat do you chiefly learne out of theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of your Chriſtian faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. <hi>J</hi> learne to beleeue, that there is a God, to beleeue God, and alſo in him. 2. That he is but one in ſubſtance, yet diſtinguiſhed into three, the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, which diſtinction is in perſon, propertie, and manner of working. 3. That this God hath a Church, to which onely he is truly knowne, and by the ſame ſincerely wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv can you be perſvvaded that there is a God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. By his created workes declaring, 2. by my conſcience accuſing: 3. by iudgements terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying: 4. by order obſerued in all things: 5. by heathen authors conſenting: 6. By the Scripture confidently auouching the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14145:11"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat is God? vve cannot tell, ther fore tell me vvhat a one he is?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> A ſpirituall ſubſtance, moſt holy, and of glorious maieſtie, infinite in his being, as euery where preſent; in wiſedome, foreſeeing &amp; rightly diſpoſing all things: in power, doing what he liſt: in iuſtice, puniſhing whom he will iuſtly: and in mercie, to ſaue whom he pleaſeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv do you behold and conceiue of this God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not by any bodily ſhape, but ſpiritually, by his word, as he hath therein manifeſted himſelfe, and by his workes, of creation, preſeruation and gouerning euery thing, according to his foreknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and appointment therein, to his owne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat beleeue you concerning God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he is God Almightie, in order the firſt perſon in the Trinitie, begetting the Sonne from euerlaſting, of his whole ſubſtance: maker of heauen and earth, men and Angels, and all things elſe very good, onely by his word, of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, at the beginning, in ſixe dayes, and ſtill by his prouidence preſerues the ſame, for my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat vvas man eſpecially made of?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Man conſiſts of bodie and ſoule, the firſt mans bodie was made of the duſt of the earth, but our bodies come by generation, and are with his mortall: and both his and all our ſoules by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are immortall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat eſtate good man in by creation, and vvhat a one did God make him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> In the eſtate of innocencie, void of all ſin, free from any puniſhment: and was made after
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14145:12"/> Gods image, that is, holy and righteous; hauing perfect knowledge of God and his will, as much as was needfull for him, and alſo readineſſe of will, in heartie affection, with bodily ſtrength, to fulfill the ſame: and had withall the rule of all Gods creatures, made for his benefite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv then came you into this vvretched e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By the fall of Adam and Eue, my firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who wilfully diſobeyed God, by the diuels enticement, infidelitie and pride poſſeſſing their hearts, and who ſtood and fell in the roome of all mankind.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv can our ſoules be ſinfull, that come not by propagation, but by inſpiration?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. For that his ſoule was deputie for all ſoules of men naturally begotten. 2. Becauſe man ſinned, and man, is not man, before body &amp; ſoule be knit together, which being conioyned, become together, as man, partaker of mans fal &amp; corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Doth any thing of that image of God remaine yet in vs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes: 1. In the mind a certaine generall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt knowledge of nature, concerning good and euill, to make vs inexcuſable, before God. 2. In the conſcience a power to reproue and repreſſe in part vnbridled affections. 3. In will, though a free, yet a weake choice, in euery naturall and ciuill action.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat euils do vve receiue by this fall?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. In the mind ignorance of heauenly things vnaptneſſe to learne them, or to iudge of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, but apt to learne euill, and to inuent the ſame. 2. In conſcience impureneſſe to excuſe ſin, not to accuſe, beeing dead or benummed: and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14145:12"/> to accuſe for well or ill doing. 3. In will, want of power, to will any true good, but to reſiſt it, and onely to will that which is euill. 4. In affection to hate good, and runne after ill. 5. In bodie fitneſſe to begin ſinne, by receiuing outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects and occaſions theteof by the ſenſes, and alſo to execute the ſame, when the heart hath concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it, in word and deed, and this is called Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne, which is in euery man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Do all men continue in this ſinfull and curſed eſtate for euer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but onely the reprobate, whome God hath not decreed to ſaue, to manifeſt his iuſtice: for the elect, being predeſtinate to eternall life, are in this world in their appointed time called effectually, through Gods word and his ſpirit, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, and ſanctified, and ſo ſhall continue, in this eſtate of grace, to be glorified, for that God will alſo ſhew his mercie, and all for his owne glorie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are none of the reprobate, euor in the eſtate of grace and Gods fauour?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No verily; though many of them, endued with the common gifts of the ſpirit, may in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, for a time, ſeeme to be of the elect, in the iudgement of the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Can any of the elect then be euer before God, in the ſtate of damnation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No indeed: albeit both before the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, and alſo after they be called, they fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by infirmitie, and lying a time in their ſinne, may appeare in ſhew, to the Church, to be none of the elect: yet can they not fall away, wholy nor finally.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>May not men then liue as they liſt, ſithence he being a reprobate, cannot be ſaued, or an elect, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be damned?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14145:13"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not ſo: for that one elected cannot but vſe the meanes, which are ordained for him to walke in, to make his election ſure to himſelfe: which whoſo doth not, cannot be ſaued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat beleeue you concerning God the Son?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he is God, the ſecond Perſon in the Trinitie, Chriſt Ieſus, the onely naturall Sonne begotten of the Father, our Lord, made man, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt, ioyning two natures into one perſon, borne, according to the promiſe, of the Virgin Marie, who perfectly fulfilled the lawe, humbled and ſuffered vnder Pontius Pylate, was crucified, bearing vpon him Gods curſe, and helliſh torments, who died and was buried, and being a while held captiue of death in the graue, he was exalted, and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly roſe againe the third day, and is aſcended vp into heauen, and there he ſits on the right hand of God his Father, hauing all power in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth to rule and gouerne his Church, where his manhood doth and ſhall at all times, (though in his Godhead he be preſent with me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer) remaine, vntill he ſhall come from thence, to iudge vs all, here on earth, both quicke and dead at the laſt day: which day cannot be nowe farre off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhy ſhould he neede to be both God and man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he might be the onely Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and man, to ſatisfie for ſinne, which neither the manhood by deſeruing, nor Godhead by dying alone could do.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhy is he called Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To declare, that he was the promiſed Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, and to ſignifie his offices, that he was annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not with materiall oyle, but with the gift of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14145:13"/> the ſpirit without meaſure, to be our King, Prieſt and Prophet: from which name we are called Chriſtians, and are by him Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv is Chriſt a King?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> He is King, not onely as God, but as hee is the head gouerning the Church, without any generall Vicar vnder him, by his word and ſpirit immediatly, making lawes, and ordeining Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to the gathering together and preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. 2. By deſtroying Sathan, his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, vnbeleeuers, idolaters, heretickes, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and the whole kingdome of darkneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv is Chriſt a prieſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. By ſatisfying for all the ſinnes of the elect, by his paſſion and fulfilling of the lawe. 2. For that he maketh prayer continually to God for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv is Chriſt a Prophet?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By immediatly reuealing from his Father, his word and meanes of ſaluation contained in the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>V<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hy is he called Ieſus?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To ſignifie that he is a Sauiour to euery true beleeuer: neither is there any other meanes of ourſelues, or by any orher, either in part or whole to obtaine ſaluation, but onely by him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhy is he called Lord?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Becauſe we owe all homage and dutie in ioue to him, for our redemption.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat beleeue you concerning the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That he is God the third perſon in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, proceeding from the Father and the Sonne who ſpake by the Prophets, dwelling in the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14145:14"/> ſanctifying them in part in this life, working by the word and holy motions, an vtter loathing of ſinne, and a heartie loue of righteouſneſſe, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them into all truth, perſwading them of Gods fauour, teaching them in prayer, bearing them vp in temptation, quickening, renewing, and increaſing his gifts in them: that they may know, beleeue, loue, and do that which is good: which he will perfect fully in the life to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhy did this God thus make, redeeme, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, and hereto preſerue you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I might prayſe his name, in liuing godly, righteouſly, and ſoberly, according to all his commandements, in my calling, in all things, whatſoeuer my eſtate be, in this preſent world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat do you beleeue concerning the Church?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That it is but one myſticall bodie, whether militant or triumphant, viſible or inviſible, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or in earth, being a companie of the Lords elect, holy by Chriſt, catholike, gathered of the diſperſed abroad, and hauing ſpeciall preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues aboue the reſt of mankind, communion with Chriſt, and one with another by the bond of the ſpirit, the forgiueneſſe of all ſinnes, the ioyfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the bodie, and life euerlaſting, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I beleeue my ſelfe to be one, and therfore, that the ſame things belong alſo vnto me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are the markes of the true Church here on earth?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Inwardly faith and loue, outwardly (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the vncertaine notes, of vniuerſalitie, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and conſent) theſe two: Chriſts word truly preached, his Sacraments rightly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14145:14"/> whereto adde, faithfull prayer, and holy diſcipline.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Js the Church of Rome a true Church of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but of Antichriſt the Pope, the chiefe teacher of the doctrine of diuels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat reaſon haue you to diſallovv that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> For that it is a falſe religion. I. The author is the diuell. II. The meanes vſed to vphold it, are vnlawfull: 1. deceiued Councels. 2. vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten verities, and forged authors: 3. falſifying the Fathers: 4. corrupting Scripture, by adding thereto. 5. by taking from it, by falſe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: 6. reteyning the people in ignorance, by forbidding to ſtudie the word, and teaching it in an vnknowne tongue: 7. pretending reuelations, and ſhewing lying miracles. 8. counterfeit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. 9. bloudie perſecution. III. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their religion is vntruthes, idolatrie, hereſie and nouelties inuented by man. IV. The forme in the ſeruice ridiculous, by fooliſh geſtures: car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, by fleſhly pompes and delights, their worſhip is by hypocriſie. V. The end to aduance men, by worſhipping of Saints, and extolling mans po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and merits. VI. The benefite gotten ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is nothing, becauſe it keepes a man in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of damnation: and alloweth the breach of all the ten Commaundements. 1. To feare God by mens doctrines. 2. To worſhip Images. 3. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke and coniuring. 4. Idol-ſeruice. 5. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt Chriſtian Princes. 6. Aſſoyles for murtherers. 7. Stewes, and reſtraint of mariage. 8. Wages for no lawfull labour, to Maſſe-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and for deceites. 9. To breake an oath to a Chriſtian made lawfully. 10. That con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14145:15"/> is no ſinne. 7. Gods iudgements, againſt many of the moſt fierie profeſſours thereof which is neuer ſeene to happen to zealous and conſtant profeſſours of the truth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat muſt be done to maintaine the Church and to ouerthrovv hereſie, that deſtroyes the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, errours, corrupting religion, ſciſmes, breaking the peace of the Church, and vices, ſtayning our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. To cleaue onely to the written word, which is both in time before, and in authoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Church, to iudge all controuerſies in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. 2. To call ſufficient men and ordaine them Miniſters to teach, allowing neceſſarie main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; but ſuffering no inſufficient to creepe in, or to abide ſtill: neither the able to liue idlely, by careleſnes, pride, or couetouſneſſe. 3. That there be a godly order eſtabliſhed and peaceably kept of euery one, without giuing offence. 4. That there be a holy and right vſe continually of true diſcipline, to admoniſh, ſuſpend, and excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate obſtinate offenders whoſoeuer they be.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are not the articles of your beleefe a prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but onely a ſumme of the Goſpell: which is one part of Gods word, containing the promiſes of ſaluation by Chriſt, and is alſo a rule by which I muſt examine my faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat meane you by faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not faith to worke miracles, which is paſt: nor hiſtoricall, onely beleeuing that to be true which God ſaith: nor temporarie, to know, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and to teach Chriſt, feare to commit ſinne, ſorrow after, to make ſatisfaction, to deſtroy the wicked, to make many prayers, wiſhing heauen, and to liue, for a time, in ſhew honeſtly, yet out of Chriſt: but iuſtifying faith is here meant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14145:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>V<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat is iuſtifying faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a gracious and true perſwaſion in my heart, grounded vpon Gods promiſes concerning Chriſt, whereby I do apply him and all his benefits to my ſelfe, being aſſured, that he is my wiſedom, ſtrength, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that what he hath done, it is as well done for me, as for any other: and ſo is mine, as if my ſelfe had done it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv came you by this faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> By the holy Ghoſt, working the ſame inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the outward miniſterie of the Goſpell prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ordinarily, &amp; is by the ſame word, Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and Prayer, confirmed, continued, and increaſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat proſite reape you by this beleefe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 
                     <hi>I</hi> a wretched ſinner in my ſelfe, being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned of ſinne, and Chriſt giuen to me; am in him the adopted ſonne of God, and righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, my heart purged, my conſcience quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, my imperfect workes do pleaſe him, all croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are for comfort and further to ſaluation: holy Angels tend vpon me, heauen is mine inheritance I am ſet at libertie from the curſe of the lawe, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, the world, and fleſhly luſts, without feare of death, damnation, and hell fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hath euery one this faith, and ſo theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but onely ſuch as ſhewe repentance, the fruite of faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat is repentance?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a true turning of my mind, will, and heart, wholly from the world, the fleſh and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, vnto God, with full purpoſe to attend care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to the counſell of his word and ſpirit, and through the whole courſe of my life, readily and conſtantly endeauour to follow the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14145:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are the true tokens of this true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. <hi>A</hi> continuall ſtriuing of the fleſh and ſpirit. 2. A hatred of my former vanities, auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding occaſion, companie, counſell, or example to ill, with loue vnfained to the contrarie. 3. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of peace in conſcience: with comfort in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for righteouſneſſe ſake. 4. <hi>A</hi> ioyfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting and wiſhing Chriſts comming to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>May not a man that truly repenteth, fall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervvards?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes indeed, and into the ſame ſinne, or ſome other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv then may a man be perſvvaded, that his repentance vvas then true before?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. If this be of infirmitie, feeling before, and in the committing a diſlike thereof: for after true repentance ſinne is neuer wholy committed. 2. If that Godly ſorrow follow, which is not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for earthly ſhame, temporall puniſhments, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh torments, or loſſe of heauen: but for diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God ſo mercifull a Father: and this is called renewed repentance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv ſhould this appeare to be true?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. By an vtter loathing and condemning my ſelfe for the ſinne newly committed, with deſire and perſwaſion of pardon. 2. <hi>A</hi> godly anger &amp; burning zeale againſt my ſelfe, with taking re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, vowing and practiſing ſtrictly the contrary vertue for offending. 3. <hi>A</hi> watchfull care and continuall feare, leſt <hi>I</hi> fall afterwards at any time againe into the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat may comfort a troubled conſcience?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Theſe things: 1. That God can pardon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinne. 2. That he will by promiſe made, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14145:16"/> euery penitent. 3. That he which feeleth a true deſire to leaue ſinne, and to pleaſe God; is bound to beleeue his ſinnes are both pardonable and pardoned. 4. That doubting of ſaluation, with feare to offend God, is a ſigne of ſaluation. 5. No condemnation to ſuch as are in Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ſinnes cannot damne them. 6. Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt not be iudged after ſanctification, there is no perfection here, and the beſt children of God haue grieuouſly fallen, and haue felt this ſting of conſcience. 7. The aſſurance of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt not be iudged as men feele aſſurance in affliction, but by the ſtabilitie of Gods promiſes, from former comforts and tokens of grace, but in trouble from preſent deſires onely.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>You ſaid, that your Godfathers and Godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did promiſe for you, that you ſhould keepe Gods commaundements, tell me hovv many there be?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Ten, and are diuided into two tables.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth the firſt table teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The dutie which I owe vnto God in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whome I muſt loue, with all my heart, with all my mind, and with all my ſoule, and with all my ſtrength, ſet downe in the foure firſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, containing the matter, manner, end, and time of Gods worſhip.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth the ſecond Table teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The dutie which <hi>I</hi> owe vnto my neighbor, which is euery one in righteouſnes, whom I muſt loue, as my ſelfe, ſet downe in the ſixe laſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, containing his dignitie, life, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, goods, credit, and more ſpiritually all of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14145:17"/>
                  <p>Q: <hi>VVhich be the Commaundements?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſame which God ſpake in the 20. of Ezodus, ſaying, I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage, which is no commaundement but the preface vnto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the firſt commandement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A,</hi> Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this Commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To make choice of one, and the true God, to be my God, and not to take that for God, which is not God by nature: the occaſion whereof was the luſting after ſtrange gods.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are the things forbidden by this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Ignorance of God and the truth, not to pray, diſtruſt of God, impatiencie, to feare, loue, or ioy in the creature more then in the Creatour, to deny God, or his word, power, preſence, iuſtice o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mercie, openly or ſecretly in heart: ſecuritie without feare of God. The contrarie is commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the ſecond Commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven image, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this Commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt neither worſhip falſe Gods, nor this true God with falſe worſhip: but in ſpirit and truth as his word onely teacheth. The occaſion of this Comman was our fooliſh deſire of a carnall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and a falſe conceipt, to be able to preſcribe a manner of worſhip to God of our ſelues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat things are hereby forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Idolatrie, picturing of God, or Chriſt, Papiſtrie, wil-worſhip, good intents without
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14145:17"/> warrant, our owne fantaſies, mens traditions, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images, pilgrimages: not to deſtroy errors, hereſies, and monuments of idolatrie. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie is commaunded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the third commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not to bereaue God of, his honour that is due vnto him: but in all things to giue him his due glorie. The occaſion of this commanndement was our readineſſe to abuſe God, his name, word, and workes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat things are hereby forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To thinke or ſpeake of God, of his word, or workes lightly or contemptuouſly, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence: to ſweare by any thing but by God: or by him, without a calling, in our ordinarie talke, where neither Gods glorie, our brothers ſaluation nor magiſtrate requireth it: to ſweare falſely. So blaſphemie, witchcraft, coniuring, and curſing: to denie the knowne truth: to profeſſe pietie, and liue wickedly: the contrarie is commaunded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the fourth commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Remember that thou keepe holy the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this Commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That euery day in the weeke I prepare my ſelfe to keepe the Lords day holy, that when it comes it be not prophaned, nor the publike worſhip of God letted, but furthered by me and mine. The occaſion of this commaundement, our aptneſſe to fall from God, without daily meanes be vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14145:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat things are hereby forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To do vnneceſſarie labours without godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and charitie, fayres, iourneys, or vaine ſports eating and drinking, that may hinder deuotion: not to heare Gods word preached, or to heare careleſly, ſleepily, with wearineſſe, or without pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to amend. To omit meditation and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. For miniſters to omit ordinarily the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, to preach in a ſtrange language vaingloriouſly, falſely, hypocritically, flattering<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or by conſtraint: without cheerefulneſſe for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to abſent themſelues negligently or wilfully from the Sacrament, the contrarie is commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the fifth commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Honour thy father and thy mother, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> To preſerue the dignitie of euery one by all meanes, that is any way to be preferred, either by his place, age, or gifts: and that no waies I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the ſame. The occaſion of this commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement was our proud and enuious nature, that cannot abide to be vnder gouernment, not to giue men their due.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat things are hereby forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Contempt of our betters, vnreuerent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour towards them, by word, or deed, to diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey their lawfull commaundements, counſels or aduice. All treaſon and rebellion. The contratie is commaunded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the ſixt Commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt do no murther.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this Commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt neither hurt nor hinder either mine owne life, or the life of my neighbour: but by all meanes preſerue the ſame. The occaſion of this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14145:18"/> commaundement, was our impatiencie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable deſire of reuenge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat things are hereby forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Want of loue, anger, malice, enuie, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, a frowning countenance, deſire of reuenge, contention, rayling, quarelling, mocking, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ieaſting, oppreſſion, fighting, murther, any bodily hurt: to neglect to vſe meanes of health, or to hinder the ſame: to be contentious, and not to ſeeke after peace. The contrarie is commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat is the ſeuenth Commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt not any way hurt or impaire the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie of my neighbour, but euery way ſeeke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſame. The occaſion of this commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was our luſtfull and fleſhly nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat things are hereby forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Luſtfull deſires, fornication, adulterie, with all occaſions hereunto: idleneſſe, wanton at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, a rolling eye, corrupt and vnhoneſt talke, wanton ſongs, laſciuious pictures, vnchaſt playes, mixt dauncing of men and women, vnſeemly ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and acts, and companying with wantons. The contrarie is commaunded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat is the eight commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I muſt not any way hinder or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh my neighbours goods, but by all meanes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and increaſe the ſame. The occaſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was our couerous nature, diſcontent euer with our preſent eſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14145:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat things are herely forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Pilfering and robberie, any way to take or keepe that which is not ours vnlawfully: all theft with all occaſions thereunto. Not to reſtore things found, borowed, or left onely to be kept of truſt: to giue what is not thine, either in whole or part. Not to liue contentedly, all couetous deſires, idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe out of calling, or litherneſſe in it: The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie is commaunded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat is the ninth commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat doth this commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I muſt not diminiſh the good name or credit of my neighbour, whither friend or foe, knowne or vnknowne: but carefully preſerue the ſame. The occaſion of this commaundement was our ſeditious nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat things are herely forbidden?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Lying in ieaſt or earneſt, backbiting, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, reuealing, ſecret infirmities and priuate offences before admonition, falſe witneſſe, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or detracting in words or ſenſe: to take a doubtfull matter in the worſt part: alſo all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to this ſinne, as enuie, diſdaine, anger, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, to be too ſuſpitious, to be readie to receiue a falſe report againſt our neighbour. The contrarie is commaunded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the tenth commaundement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Thou ſhalt not couer, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat doth this Commaundement teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I may not haue once an vnlawfull luſt to that which is my neighbours: but for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thinke good towards him. The occaſion of<gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                        <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14145:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a right requeſt made onely to God, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, by a true beleeuer, for ſuch things as be lawfull</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat rule haue you to direct you in your prayer aright?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſame which our Sauiour Chriſt taught his diſciples, called the Lords prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Let me heare it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv many parts are thereof this prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Foure: I. a preface: II. ſixe petitions: III. a confirmation. IV. a concluſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich is the preface?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is contained in theſe words, <hi>Our Father vvhich art in heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat learne you out of this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. That a preparation muſt be made to pray. 2. It ſhewes the properties of true prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat muſt you aforehand prepare, in going to God to pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. I muſt prepare theſe 6. things. My mind to meditate of heauenly things, before I ſet to pray, and vnderſtand that it is commaunded and promiſed, what I purpoſe to aske. 2. My heart, withdrawing it from former paſſions a while, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect earneſtly with feruencie that I will aske. 3. My words to be vttered aptly with the heart agreeing with the matter. 4. My behauiour to a holy reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, conſidering Gods iuſtice and maieſtie, and my wickedneſſe and baſeneſſe. 5. My faith, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend as much as ſhall be neceſſarie. 6. My hope to waite without appointing God either the time, place, manner, or quantitie of the matter. 7. My will, to vſe afterwards all the honeſt meanes appointed to obtaine the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14145:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat be the true properties of prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. That it be in true loue: for we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to pray for all our brethren not departed this life, for there is no Purgatorie. 2. It muſt bee made onely to God, for him only can we call hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, neither to Saints nor Angels. 3. In the name of Chriſt, through whom onely he is our Father by adoption. 4. In faith: for that he is a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and will not deny his children. 5. Without a carnall conceipt of God, vaine babling, or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thoughts: for he is in heauen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich be the ſixe petitions?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Hallowed be thy name, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat do theſe teach you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſumme of all the things which <hi>I</hi> can lawfully aske at Gods hand, for body or ſoule: wherof the firſt three concerne the glorie of God, and the latter three the good of man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich is the firſt petition, and vvhat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you in it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The firſt is, <hi>Hallovved be thy name:</hi> and I deſire therein, in the firſt place, that I and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may acknowledge God ſo truly, in his word and workes, as in euery of our thoughts, wordes, and deeds, he may be highly worſhipped and prayſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich is the ſecond, and vvhat deſire you in it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A</label> The ſecond is, <hi>Thy kingdome come:</hi> and deſire that he will ſend vs the meanes, thus to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his name, that is, his word and ſpirit: with all things that do further thereunto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſo the elect may be gathered, and Chriſt come to the laſt iudgement to giue vs his kingdome of glorie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich is the third petition, and vvhat deſire you in it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14145:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The third is, <hi>Thy vvill be done,</hi> and I deſire, that as we haue the meanes to glorifie him, ſo here we pray to do, not ours, but his will, as all his commaundements and word teacheth vs: and as the bleſſed Saints and Angels do in heauen, heartily wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hout hypocriſie, willingly without grudging, readily without lingring, faithfully without ſiniſter reſpects, ioyfully without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and conſtantly without wauering vnto the end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich is the fourth petition, and vvhat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you in it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The fourth is, <hi>Giue vs this, &amp;c.</hi> and I deſire, that he will provide thoſe neceſſaries for our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, without which we cannot ſerue him: and that we may depend patiently vpon his prouidence, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing diligent labour, and all honeſt meanes to helpe our ſelues and others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich is the fifth petition, and vvhat deſire you in it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The fifth is, <hi>And forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, &amp;c</hi> and I deſire, that he would forgiue all of vs, friend or foe, our ſinnes, leſt they either hinder vs of the former mercies, or cauſe them to be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: and that he will perſwade our conſciences, that we are forgiuen, by giuing vs grace to forgiue freely, and to forget thoſe offences, whereby in any thing, or any way, our neighbours haue bene grieuous vnto vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhich is the ſixt and laſt petition, and vvhat deſire you in it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The ſixth is, <hi>Leade vs not into temptation, &amp;c.</hi> and I deſire, that as he will pardon vs, ſo he would alſo giue vs the gift of continuance, that though we be tempted, yet may we ouercome, and be deliuered from ſinne and Sathan, and neuer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14145:21"/> fall againe any more from God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hich is the confirmation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> For thine is the kingdome, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat learne you by this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 
                     <hi>I</hi> do learne hereby two things: 1. that it is a reaſon, not to moue God, but to ſtir vp our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and to ſtrengthen our faith in asking.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv doth it this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> When it teacheth me to acknowledge the kingdome to God our Father, that is, his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and right ouer all: and that his power is the greateſt to compell all to do what he will, and as he will: and his glorie the higheſt, which himſelf maintaines, and we ſeeke aboue all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the ſecond thing vve learne?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 2. A thankſgiuing and prayſing of God, which we ought to vſe in the end, as the ſecond part of prayer: which is done, in giuing to God his owne, the rule, power, and glorie, which we deſire him to manifeſt by graunting our petitions, and we will acknowledge the ſame; not for a time, but for euer and euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hich is the concluſion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> This word, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat meane you by this vvord?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> That I am perſwaded by the aforeſaid rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that my requeſt is graunted, and ſhall bee performed, as my father ſhall ſee it conuenient for me and his glorie, in time and place. And therefore I ſay, <hi>it is ſo,</hi> or <hi>ſo it ſhall be,</hi> which is <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>The fifth part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is a Sacrament?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14145:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is a viſible ſigne and ſeale of inuiſible graces, commaunded and ordained with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe by Chriſt in the Church, to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred publikely, by a lawfull Miniſter, with the preaching of the word: which Sacrament with all the rites thereof doth repreſent and conuey by proportion and relation, in the preſent vſe, inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible graces, firſt, Chriſt, and then all his benefites, for further aſſurance of the ſame things, which God hath made by the promiſe of his word, vnto a true beleeuer, who is with Chriſt by the holy Ghoſt, vnited and made one.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat meane you by Chriſt, &amp; all his benefits?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Whole Chriſt, God and man, with his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, iuſtice, holines, and redemption: who as he is Chriſt, one perſon of two natures, is truly ſaid to be really preſent in the Sacraments, not properly in his humanitie, but by the communion of properties.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv may you be ſure that you haue receiued true benefite by the Sacraments?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> If I do feele a dying to ſinne, and liuing vnto righteouſneſſe, getting ſtrength, and alſo increaſing therein daily, by the force of Chriſtes death and reſurrection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv many Sacraments are there?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Two and no moe: Baptiſme and the Lords Supper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhat is Baptiſme?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is the firſt Sacrament in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which ſuch as are within the couenant, are either waſhed, ſprinkled, or dipped in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the outvvard ſigne and rite?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Water and waſhing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14145:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the inuiſible grace?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The bloud of Chriſt which cleanſeth vs of all ſinne, originall and actuall, paſt and to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Are vve then no more ſinners?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Yes in ourſelues: for originall ſinne ſtill is ſinne in vs, but we are waſhed from it. becauſe it ſhall not be imputed, nor any ſinne elſe vnto me a true beleeuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVho are to be baptized?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Not onely ſuch as be of yeares, that can &amp; do teſtifie their faith: but alſo infants of either fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or mother profeſſing Chriſt and baptized: for the promiſe of ſaluation belongs to them and to their children.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Is baptiſme ſo neceſſarie to ſaluation, that vvithout it children cannot be ſaued?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> It is neceſſarie, to all that may haue it, but not of neceſſitie, to ſuch as cannot rightly come by it: for not the want, but the careleſſe neglect and contempt thereof condemneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv oft ſhould vve be baptized?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> But once, for we may not be baptized againe after true baptiſme: for being once borne, we cannot be borne againe naturally, nor ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat is the Lords Supper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is the latter Sacrament in the new Teſtament whereby we are nouriſhed and preſerued in the Church to eternall life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat be the outvvard ſignes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>B. Bread and wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat be the things ſignified?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The bodie and bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Vhat are the rites?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> The actions of the Miniſter and receiuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are the actions of the Miniſter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14145:22"/>
                  <p>A. 1. To take the bread &amp; wine into his hands. 2. to bleſſe it. 3. To breake the bread, and powre foorth the wine. 4. to offer and giue them to the receiuer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat are the actions of the receiuer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. To take the bread and wine offered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand, 2. to eate the one, and drinke the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo digeſt and concoct them, as that they feele nouriſhment to the bodie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> you by all theſe actions?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am aſſured, that the viſible actions of the Miniſter, doth repreſent the ſpirituall actions of God the Father to my ſoule, who hath decreed his Sonne, and elected him the Mediator, to haue his bodie broked, and his precious bloud ſhed for me, being offered to all, but giuen onely to the true beleeuer, that can by the hand of faith take hold of him: who ſhewes as liuely the vertue of his death to preſerue his ſoule, as the vertue of the bread and wine is felt to nouriſh the bodie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the bread turned into Chriſts bodie, and is the wine into his very bloud?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No verily: for then, 1. it were no Sacrament, 2. it is againſt reaſon, 3. againſt Scripture, 4. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an article of our Creed, 5. againſt the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of anncient Fathers true writings, 6. againſt the iudgement of reformed Chriſtian Churches, 7. againſt the opinion of holy Martyrs, who ſhed their bloud for the contrarie, 8. it is againſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of our ſenſes, that the bread ſhould bee fleſh, or wine, bloud: neither is Chriſts bodie in, with, or about the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Is there then no difference of this bread and vvine, from that vvhich vve vſe commonly?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> There is no difference in the ſubſtance, but in the holy vſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being at that time ſet apart to be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14145:23"/> ſignes of Chriſts bodie and bloud.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>May euery one offer to receiue the vvill?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: but onely ſuch: as come prepared, and be fit, that both are able in knowledge to examin, and alſo by a good conſcience will iudge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, whither they be in any meaſure prepared thereunto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat if you come vnprepared?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I am an vnworthie receiuer, prouoking Gods wrath againſt me, and ſo eate and drinke my owne damnation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVho are thoſe that ought not to come?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> Open impenitent ſinners, fooles, madde perſons, children, all that be of yeares, and yet ignorant, not being able to trie and iudge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and if ſuch prophane ones do offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they are not to be admitted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhat be thoſe things vvhereof you muſt try and iudge your ſelues?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I. Of my knowledge, concerning my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate through ſinne, of Gods mercie; and our deliuerance by Chriſt, and the vnderſtanding of this Sacrament. II. Of my beleefe in Chriſt, which I may do by the Creede. III. Of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance towards God, for old and new ſinnes, examined by his commaundements. IV. Of my brotherly loue, which <hi>I</hi> do owe to euery one, which I may trie and iudge by my forgiuing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as I deſire God to forgiue me, and by my ſeeking to ſatisfie whom I haue offended of my knowledge either in word or deed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>May any by omitting theſe duties be free from ſinne, if therefore they vvill not receiue the Sacrament vvith others?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> No: for as to come vnprepared is damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo to neglect to prepare for any earthly occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14145:23"/> is a great wickedneſſe, ſuch liuing in diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, without repentance and charitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>VVhy do you go to the Lords ſupper?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> 1. To teſtifie my loue in obedience to God commaunding. 2. To ſtrengthen my faith beeing weake. 3. To maintaine and increaſe the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and fellowſhip of brotherly loue amongſt vs the members of Chriſt and 4. to keepe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his death till his ſecond comming.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Hovv muſt you be exerciſed in the time of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and aftervvards?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>A.</label> I muſt. 1. meditate vpon the death and paſſion of Chriſt, how grieuouſly I haue ſinned. 2. Gods endleſſe mercie. 3. the vnitie and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip that is amongſt the true members of the Church with Chriſt, and one with another: reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in heart, and prayſing God therefore with the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Afterwards 1. I muſt giue almes to the needie brethren, and do other good works of charitie in token of thankfulneſſe, that day e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, for ſo great a mercie. 2. Grow from thenceforth in obedience, faith, and vnfained loue to my liues end.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>The ſixt part.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <label>Q.</label> 
                     <hi>Can you briefly ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vv me any rules to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that you may do ſo, as you haue bene taught?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>A.</label> I. Euery morning before other buſineſſe, I muſt 1. thanke God for my ſafetie, 2. deſire par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſinne, 3. Gods further protection againſt ghoſtly and bodily enemies.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. I muſt know that, that day, and all other times after giuen me to liue in, are for more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repentance, encreaſe of knowledge, faith, &amp;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14145:24"/> practiſe of godlineſſe: and therefore of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually I muſt be mindfull, ſetting ſome part of the day aſide for reading, hearing, or meditating vpon heauenly things: that the vanities of the world ſhort and vncertaine carie me not away.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. I muſt haue, or elſe prepare my ſelfe to ſome particular calling, fit to keepe me from idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to exerciſe the duties of religion, in which calling muſt I be both honeſt, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to others, to which 1. I muſt betake me ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily that no time be loſt. 2. to do therein as I wold be done vnto. 3. to ſeeke firſt in my labour Gods glorie, then my owne good with my neighbours profite. 4. labour therein painefully and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in aduerſitie vſing good meanes hoping for proſperitie, in proſperitie neglecting no humble duties for feare of aduerſitie. 5. my preſent eſtate I muſt account it euer the beſt for me, and moſt for Gods glorie. 6. I muſt not feare to ſpend where God and charitie requireth, ſparing from idle expences, and onely lay vp, for the time to come, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tſoeuer ſhall remaine, when I haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged neceſſarie duties, honeſtly &amp; religiouſly.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. I muſt recreate my ſelfe ſometime from my weariſome labour, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſee need, which muſt be 1. at times conuenient. 2. in things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. 3. ſhort, delightſome to the mind, &amp; health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the bodie. 4. to make me more chearefull to returne to labour, and not to draw me to loiter &amp; to idlenes, no end appointed to man nor beaſt.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. I muſt warily ſee to mine owne waies. 1. My thoughts and heart muſt 1. be far from vnlawfull affection. 2. vpon lawfull things on earth mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and no more then needes. 3. vpon God and heauenly things often, feruently, and reuerently. 4 that I ſtriue againſt ſelfe-loue, thinking of my
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14145:24"/> ſelfe baſely; and waxe, by more and greater gifts, the more humble and leſſe enuious 5. On others I muſt thinke highly, and charitably, iudging wel without ſuſpitions what <hi>I</hi> heare or ſee good in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, receiuing it with ioy: and hoping of better what I ſee or heare to be ill in them, taking doubtfull words or deeds from them in the better part. II. My eyes muſt be ſhut againſt obiects to ſinne, that they let them not into my heart, to ſtine vp ill mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but quicke to obſerue euery good example and occaſion to goodneſſe. III. My eares muſt be exerciſed in hearing the truth, good counſels, friendly admonitions, and godly exhortations, but ſhut againſt flatterie, lyings, ſlaunder, filthie and wicked ſpeeches. IV. My tongue muſt keepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, vnleſſe iuſt cauſe and conuenient time and place be to ſpeake. In ſpeaking the matter muſt 1. be gracious to profit the hearers, and alſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to be vttered. 2. in wiſedome regarding cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. 3. in ſinceritie to ſpeake it from the heart. 4. ſpeaking of God and his word, it muſt be religiouſly and ioyfully: of ourſelues modeſtly: of others louingly. 5. to prayſe moderately without contempt: to diſprayſe meekely ſhewing loue, to be conſtrained by neceſſitie, rather then of will, to ſpeake of other mens faults, expreſſing ſorow in vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering. 6. to ſpeake well of men in abſence, what good we know of them, and to defend them, and in preſence without flatterie. 7. to vſe few wordes and effectuall to the matter without tediouſneſſe. 8. not to talke of needleſſe matters, or which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne vs nor, as buſi-bodies, neither of any thing, againſt religion, charitie, common good, or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie. V. My behauiour, 1. it muſt be lowly to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, 2. gentle to inferiours, and 3. louely to familiars. VI. My apparell it muſt be firſt for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14145:25"/> and then for honeſt decencie, as we are able, and agreeing with our calling. VII. My diet muſt be 1. ſparing, ordinarily a kind of faſting, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a feaſting. 2. taking my foode with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſting. 3. at ſeaſonable howers. 4. that thereby 1. my ſtrength may be maintained and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, 2. my meditation and deuotion nothing hindred. 5. that we be prepared in the beginning may feele a neceſſitie and pray to God: and in the end ſufficient refreſhing, may thanke God.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. <hi>J</hi> muſt take heed what companie I keepe with, 1. that <hi>J</hi> make my familiars none but honeſt and religious, 2. that they be my equals in eſtate and place, not ſuperiours, to auoid ſuſpition of pride: nor too much inferiour, leaſt it bring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. 3. that of theſe, not many, but one of all, I warily, deliberately, and with much triall, chuſe my ſecret friend. 4. that in going or keeping with any, <hi>J</hi> muſt euer purpoſe either to do good, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſome.</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. At night, the time of reſt, 1. I muſt call to mind Gods benefites receiued, either by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting euill, or by bringing good vpon me, to thanke him. 2. <hi>J</hi> muſt recount what I haue done, either in euill to repent, or what good I performed to iudge either of my increaſing or decaying in grace: ſorowing more for the duties omitted and ſinnes committed, then ioyfull of any good done. 3. In taking reſt I muſt commit my ſelfe to God, by a deuout and faithfull prayer, as thinking no more to riſe. 4. to haue my laſt thoughts of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things, by committing or recalling ſomwhat to mind, of I haue either heard or learned out of Gods word. 5. that I take ſleepe to refreſh nature and not to ſatisfie ſlouthfull fleſh.</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. And laſt is, that all the weeke long I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14145:25"/> remember ſo to labour in my calling, and diſpoſe of my ordinarie buſineſſe, that I be prepared for the Lords day to keepe it holy: but eſpecially at the end of the weeke, ſo that when it comes, I may neither by them breake it, or be hindred. Thus liuing to God holly, to my neighbour chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, and towards my ſelfe ſoberly, my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall be comforted, my weake brethren ſtrengthened, the ſtrong confirmed, the wicked made aſhamed, the diuell confounded, and God greatly glorified.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
